What's the most important century in human history?
मानव इतिहास की सबसे महत्वपूर्ण सदी कौन सी है?
Some might argue it’s a period of extensive military campaigning,
कुछ कहेंगे की यह शीर्षक हम किसी व्यापक सैन्य विजय के काल को दे सकते हैं,
like Alexander the Great’s in the 300s BCE,
जैसे चौथवी शताब्दी ईसा पूर्व को, जिसमे सिकन्दर ने अपने अभियान से
which reshaped political and cultural borders.
राजनीतिक एवं सांस्कृतिक सीमाओं को परिवर्तित कर दिया था।
Others might cite the emergence of a major religion,
दूसरे शायद किसी प्रमुख धर्म के उद्गमन की सदी को यह जगह देंगे,
such as Islam in the 7th century,
जैसे की सातवी सदी, जिसमे इस्लाम का जन्म हुआ था,
which codified and spread values across such borders.
जिससे मूल्यों का संहिताकरण और विस्तार दूर-दूर तक हो गया।
Or perhaps it’s the Industrial Revolution of the 1700s
या फिर शायद यह शीर्षक अठारवी सदी की औद्योगिक क्रांति को दिया जाना चाहिए,
that transformed global commerce
जिसने वैश्विक व्यापार को बदल दिया,
and redefined humanity's relationship with labor.
और मानवता और श्रम के रिश्ते को एक नयी परिभाषा दी।
Whatever the answer, it seems like any century vying for that top spot
चाहे जवाब कुछ भी हो, ऐसा प्रतीत होता है की इस शीर्षक के लिए टकराने वाली सदियां
is at a moment of great change—
एक बड़े बदलाव के बीच में है,
when the actions of our ancestors shifted humanity’s trajectory
जिसके दौरान हमारे पूर्वजों के फैसलों ने मानवता के भविष्य
for centuries to come.
को हमेशा के लिए बदल दिया।
So if this is our metric, is it possible that right now—
तो अगर यह ही हमारा पैमाना है, क्या ऐसा हो सकता है की अभी—
this century— is the most important one yet?
यही सदी—अब तक की सबसे महत्वपूर्ण है?
The 21st century has already proven to be a period of rapid technological growth.
इक्कीसवी सदी ने अपने आप को एक तेज़ तकनीकी विकास की सदी साबित किया है।
Phones and computers have accelerated the pace of life.
फोनों और कम्प्यूटरों ने ज़िंदगी की गति बढ़ा दी है।
And we’re likely on the cusp of developing new transformative technologies,
और हम कई नयी परिवर्तनकारी तकनीकों पर काम कर रहें हैं,
like advanced artificial intelligence,
जैसे की उच्च कृत्रिम बुद्धि (AI),
that could entirely change the way people live.
जो हमारे रहन-सहन के तरीके को पूरी तरह से बदल सकती है।
Meanwhile, many technologies we already have
और इस दौरान जो प्रोद्योगिकाएँ हमारे पास पहले से मौजूद है
contribute to humanity’s unprecedented levels of existential risk—
वो मानवता को और भी अधिक अस्तित्वगत जोखिम में दाल रही हैं-
that’s the risk of our species going extinct
यानि यह खतरा की हमारी प्रजाति विलुप्त हो सकती है,
or experiencing some kind of disaster that permanently limits
या फिर किसी ऐसे खतरे का सामना कर सकती है जिससे मानवता की बढ़ने की क्षमता
humanity’s ability to grow and thrive.
हमेशा के लिए सीमित हो सकती है।
The invention of the atomic bomb marked a major rise in existential risk,
परमाणु हथियारों के आविष्कार से अस्तित्वगत जोखिम में काफी बढ़ोतरी हुई,
and since then we’ve only increased the odds against us.
और तब से हम खतरे के और करीब आते ही जा रहे हैं।
It’s profoundly difficult to estimate the odds
इसी सदी में किसी बड़ी अस्तित्वगत दुर्घटना की संभावना
of an existential collapse occurring this century.
का अनुमान लगाना बड़ा मुश्किल है।
Very rough guesses put the risk of existential catastrophe
बहुत मोटे अनुमान जलवायु परिवर्तन या नाभिकीय शीतकाल
due to nuclear winter and climate change at around 0.1%,
द्वारा वैश्विक विपत्तिपूर्ण जोखिम होने की संभावना का अनुमान 0.1 % लगाते हैं,
with the odds of a pandemic causing the same kind of collapse
जब की इतनी ही एक घातक महामारी
at a frightening 3%.
की सम्भावना 3% है।
Given that any of these disasters could mean the end of life as we know it,
यह देखते हुए की इनमे से कोई भी घटनाएँ सारे जीवन को ख़त्म कर सकती हैं,
these aren’t exactly small figures,
यह बहुत छोटे आंकड़ों नहीं हैं,
And it’s possible this century could see the rise of new technologies
और यह भी संभव है की इस सदी में होने वाले अविष्कार
that introduce more existential risks.
अस्तित्वगत जोखिम को और बढ़ा दे।
AI experts have a wide range of estimates regarding
AI विशेषज्ञ अलग-अलग अनुमान लगाते है
when artificial general intelligence will emerge,
की कृत्रिम सामान्य बुद्धि कब उभर के सामने आएगी,
but according to some surveys, many believe it could happen this century.
पर कुछ सर्वेक्षणों के हिसाब से यह इस सदी में ही हो सकता है।
Currently, we have relatively narrow forms of artificial intelligence,
अपने वर्तमान रूप मे कृत्रिम बुद्धि काफी कम और विशिष्ट कार्य ही कर सकती हैं,
which are designed to do specific tasks like play chess or recognize faces.
जिन्हे विशिष्ट कार्यों, जैसे शतरंज खलेने या चेहरे पहचानने, के लिए बनाया गया है।
Even narrow AIs that do creative work are limited to their singular specialty.
रचनात्मक कार्य करने वाली कृत्रिम बुद्धि भी सिर्फ अपने विशेष क्षेत्र तक ही सीमित है।
But artificial general intelligences, or AGIs,
लेकिन कृत्रिम सामान्य बुद्धियाँ, या AGIs,
would be able to adapt to and perform any number of tasks,
अपने आप को बदल कर अलग-अलग कार्य भी कर सकेंगी,
quickly outpacing their human counterparts.
और वो भी इंसानो से बेहतर।
There are a huge variety of guesses about what AGI could look like,
इस बात पर अलग-अलग अनुमान है की यह AGI कैसी दिखेगी,
and what it would mean for humanity to share the Earth
और मानवता एक और चेतना वाली ईकाई के साथ
with another sentient entity.
इस पृथ्वी पर कैसे रह पाएगी।
AGIs might help us achieve our goals,
AGIs शायद हमारे लक्ष्य पूरे करने मे हमारी सहायता करें,
they might regard us as inconsequential,
हमें महत्वहीन समझें,
or, they might see us as an obstacle to swiftly remove.
या हमें एक बाधा के रूप में देखें जिसे वह तेज़ी से हटाना चाहें।
So in terms of existential risk,
तो फिर अस्तित्वगत जोखिम के मामले में
it's imperative the values of this new technology align with our own.
यह अनिवार्य होगा की इस नई तकनीक के मूल्य और विश्वास हमसे मिलते हो।
This is an incredibly difficult philosophical and engineering challenge
यह एक बहुत ही मुश्किल दार्शनिक और इंजीनियरिंग चुनौती होगी,
that will require a lot of delicate, thoughtful work.
जिससे हमें बहुत ही नज़ाकत और ध्यान से निपटना पड़ेगा।
Yet, even if we succeed, AGI could still lead to another complicated outcome.
इतनी मेहनत के बावजूद भी AGI हमें एक जटिल परिणाम की ओर ले जा सकती है।
Let’s imagine an AGI emerges with deep respect for human life
एक ऐसी AGI की कल्पना करते हैं जो मानव जीवन का आदर करती हो
and a desire to solve all humanity’s troubles.
और मानवता की सारी मुश्किलों को हल करना चाहती हो ।
But to avoid becoming misaligned,
लेकिन, ताकि यह कभी इन मूल्यों को भूल ना जाए,
it's been developed to be incredibly rigid about its beliefs.
उसे अपनी इन मान्यताओं के प्रति बहुत कठोर भी बनाया गया हो।
If these machines became the dominant power on Earth,
अगर यह मशीनें पृथ्वी पर प्रमुख शक्तियां बन गयी,
their strict values might become hegemonic,
तो इनकी यह कठोर मान्यताएं हम सब पर भारी होकर
locking humanity into one ideology that would be incredibly resistant to change.
मानवता को एक ऐसी विचारधारा में बंद कर सकती हैं जिससे निकलना बहुत कठिन हो जायेगा।
History has taught us that no matter how enlightened
इतिहास हमें यह सिखाता है की चाहे एक सभ्यता
a civilization thinks they are,
अपने आप को जितना भी प्रबुद्ध समझे,
they are rarely up to the moral standards of later generations.
वह आने वाली पीढ़ियों के नैतिक मानकों पर कभी सफल नहीं हो पाएंगी।
And this kind of value lock in could permanently distort or constrain
और नैतिक मूल्यों में ऐसा फस जाना मानवता के नैतिक विकास
humanity’s moral growth.
को हमेशा के लिए बिगाड़ सकता है।
There's a ton of uncertainty around AGI,
अभी भी AGI के मुद्दे पर काफी अनिश्चितता है,
and it’s profoundly difficult to predict how any existential risks
और इस बात का अनुमान लगाना बहुत मुश्किल है की अगली सदी में
will play out over the next century.
इससे कितना अस्तित्वगत जोखिम होगा।
It’s also possible that new, more pressing concerns
यह भी संभव है की कुछ नए और ज़्यादा ज्वलंत मुद्दे
might render these risks moot.
इन जोखिमों से हमारा ध्यान हटा दें।
But even if we can't definitively say that ours is the most important century,
पर चाहे हम अपनी इस सदी को इतिहास की सबसे महत्वपूर्ण सदी कह पाएं या न कह पाएं,
it still seems like the decisions we make might have a major impact
ऐसा संभव है की जो निर्णय हम आज लेंगे उनका मानवता के भविष्य पर
on humanity’s future.
भारी असर होगा।
So maybe we should all live like the future depends on us—
तो शायद हम सबको ऐसे जीना चाहिए जैसे सारा भविष्य हम पर ही निर्भर करता हो-
because actually, it just might.
क्योंकि शायद वह वास्तव मे करता हो।